Emily J. Shumchenia, PhD

E&C Enviroscape, LLC Rhode Island, USA (401) 226-4294

emily.shumchenia@gmail.com

Q www.eshumchenia.com

♡ @hi em

Emily has over ten years of experience practicing science and science communication. In 2014, she established E&C Enviroscape to assist clients in science-based decision-making. This work has included project management, facilitation, data synthesis and visualization, writing, and graphics development. Emily is skilled at synthesizing and distilling scientific information into simple and clear communication products. Through E&C Enviroscape she has worked with teams in government, academia, industry, and non-profit organizations.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Principal, E&C Enviroscape, LLC

2014 - present

- Northeast Ocean Plan and Northeast Ocean Data Portal | Northeast Regional Ocean Council | www.neoceanplanning.org | www.northeastoceandata.org
- Support to Mid-Atlantic Regional Planning Body Ecologically Rich Areas Work Group | Monmouth University
- Developing an indicator monitoring and assessment program to support Mid-Atlantic Regional Ocean Action Plan Healthy Ocean Ecosystem Action 5 | Mid-Atlantic Regional Council on the Ocean
- Advancing the Biological Condition Gradient Framework for US Estuaries | US EPA Region 1, US EPA Biocriteria Program, Narragansett Bay Estuary Program
- Diver outreach to support the Black Sea Bass stock assessment | Integrated Statistics, NOAA Northeast Fisheries Science Center
- Mid-Atlantic Regional Ocean Assessment | Mid-Atlantic Regional Council on the Ocean | www.roa.midatlanticocean.org
- Ecological synthesis and classification of submerged marine habitats in Cape Cod National Seashore, Massachusetts | Center for Coastal Studies, National Park Service
- Post-Hurricane Sandy submerged marine habitat mapping, Fire Island National Seashore | University of Rhode Island Graduate School of Oceanography, National Park Service

Freelance marine scientist

2013 - 2014

- Seafloor and habitat mapping | Maine Coastal Mapping Initiative, Maine Coastal Program | https://www.maine.gov/DACF/mcp/planning/mcmi/index.htm
- Topo-bathy data modeling on Cape Cod, Massachusetts | Center for Coastal Studies
- Review of marine habitat classification, characterization, and modeling activities in the Northeast US | Coastal Vision, LLC, Northeast Regional Ocean Council

May 2017 1

Postdoctoral fellow

University of Rhode Island Graduate School of Oceanography

2010 - 2013

- Narragansett Bay benthic biotope characterization and habitat quality assessment | Rhode Island Sea Grant, US EPA Region 1
- Application of the Coastal and Marine Ecological Classification Standard (CMECS) to the Northwest Atlantic | The Nature Conservancy, Massachusetts Division of Marine Fisheries, North Atlantic Landscape Conservation Cooperative
- Seafloor mapping of Long Island Sound Phase 1 Pilot Project | Long Island Sound Mapping and Research Collaborative: University of Connecticut, University of New Haven, USGS
- Developing environmental protocols and monitoring tools to support ocean renewable energy and stewardship | National Oceanographic Partnership Program
- Benthic habitat distribution and subsurface geology in selected sites from the Rhode Island Ocean Special Area Management Plan study area | Rhode Island Coastal Resources Management Council

Graduate research assistant

University of Rhode Island Graduate School of Oceanography

2005 - 2010

- Dissertation: Benthic habitat mapping and assessment using organism-sediment relationships
- Coordinated Narragansett BayMap Project (RI Sea Grant) and collaboration with USDA-NRCS subaqueous soils mapping in Narragansett Bay (MapCoast Partnership)

EDUCATION

2010 PhD, Oceanography, University of Rhode Island

2005 BS, Marine biology, University of Rhode Island

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Visit my google scholar page

- **Shumchenia EJ,** Guarinello ML, King JW. 2016. A re-assessment of Narragansett Bay benthic habitat quality between 1988 and 2008. Estuaries and Coasts 39: 1463-1477.
- **Shumchenia EJ**, Guarinello ML, Carey DA, Lipsky A, Greene J, Mayer L, Nixon ME, Weber J. 2015. Inventory and comparative evaluation of seabed mapping, classification and modeling activities in the Northwest Atlantic, USA to support regional ocean planning. Journal of Sea Research 100: 133-140.
- **Shumchenia EJ**, Pelletier MC, Cicchetti G, Pesch CE, Pryor M, and Deacutis CF. 2015. A biological condition gradient model for historical assessment of estuarine habitat structure. Journal of Environmental Management 55:143-158.
- Grilli AR, and **Shumchenia EJ**. 2015. Toward wind farm monitoring optimization: assessment of ecological zones from marine landscapes using machine learning algorithms. Hydrobiologia 756:117-137.
- **Shumchenia EJ**, Smith SL, McCann J, Carnevale M, Fugate G, Kenney RD, King JW, Paton P, Schwartz M, Spaulding M, and Winiarski KJ. 2012. An adaptive framework for selecting environmental monitoring protocols to support ocean renewable energy

May 2017 2

- development. Scientific World Journal 2012: Article ID 450685 doi:10.1100/2012/450685.
- Galparsoro I, Connor DW, Borja Á, et al. 2012. Using EUNIS habitat classification for benthic mapping in European seas: present concerns and future needs. Marine Pollution Bulletin 64: 2630-2638.
- Stolt M, Bradley M, Turenne J, Payne M, Scherer E, Cicchetti G, King J, **Shumchenia E**, Guarinello M, Boothroyd J, Oakley B, Thornber C, and August P. 2011. Methods and protocols for mapping shallow subtidal benthic habitats. Journal of Coastal Research 27: 1-15.
- **Shumchenia EJ** and King JW. 2010. Comparison of methods for integrating biological and physical data for marine habitat mapping and classification. Continental Shelf Research 30: 1717-1729.
- **Shumchenia EJ** and King JW. 2010. Evaluation of sediment profile imagery as a tool for assessing water quality in Greenwich Bay, Rhode Island, USA. Ecological Indicators 10: 818-825.
- Guarinello ML, **Shumchenia EJ,** and King JW. 2010. Marine habitat classification for ecosystem-based management: A proposed hierarchical framework. Environmental Management 45, 793-806.

OTHER PUBLICATIONS

- Weaver KJ, **Shumchenia EJ**, Ford KH, Rousseau MA, Greene JK, Anderson MG, and King JW. 2013. Application of the Coastal and Marine Ecological Classification Standard (CMECS) to the Northwest Atlantic. The Nature Conservancy, Eastern Division Conservation Science, Eastern Regional Office. Boston, MA. http://nature.ly/EDcmecs
- McCann J, et al. 2012. Developing Environmental Protocols and Modeling Tools to Support Ocean Renewable Energy and Stewardship. U.S. Department of the Interior, Bureau of Ocean Energy Management, Office of Renewable Energy Programs, Herndon, VA, OCS Study BOEM 2012-082, 626 pp.
- Pesch CE, **Shumchenia EJ**, Charpentier M, and Pelletier MC. 2012. Imprint of the past: Ecological history of Greenwich Bay, Rhode Island. EPA/600/R-12/050. US Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Research and Development, National Health and Environmental Effects Laboratory, Atlantic Ecology Division, Narragansett, RI.
- LaFrance M, **Shumchenia EJ**, King JW, Pockalny RA, Oakley BA, Pratt SD, and Boothroyd JC. 2010. Benthic habitat distribution and subsurface geology in selected sites from the Rhode Island Ocean Special Area Management Plan study area. Technical report for Rhode Island Ocean Special Area Management Plan, University of Rhode Island, Kingston, RI. pp. 294-391.
- **Shumchenia EJ** and King JW. 2010. Assessment of shallow water habitat mapping tools and methods: A pilot study at Fire Island National Seashore. Natural Resource Technical Report NPS/NERO/NRTR 2010/323. National Park Service, Fort Collins, Colorado.

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

May 2017 3

Reviewer for: Applied Geography, ESRI Press, Estuarine Coastal and Shelf Science, International Journal of Geo-Information, Journal of Applied Ecology, Journal of Environmental Planning and Management, Journal of Sea Research, Marine Ecology Progress Series, New York Sea Grant, The Nature Conservancy

2012 - present	Senior fellow, Coastal Institute, University of Rhode Island
2009 – present	FGDC Review/Implementation Group member, Coastal and Marine Ecological Classification Standard (NOAA and NatureServe)
2005 - present	Steering committee member, J Stanley Cobb Endowment
2013	Session co-chair, ASLO Aquatic Science Meeting, New Orleans LA
2012	Pre-selection judge for the <i>Grantham Prize for Excellence in Environmental Reporting</i> , Metcalf Institute for Environmental Reporting
2007	Judge, National Ocean Sciences Bowl
2006 – 2010	Science educator, Annual Workshop for Journalists, Metcalf Institute for Environmental Reporting
2005	Faculty search committee student member, Department of Biological Sciences, University of Rhode Island
2004 – 2005	Peer mentor, Department of Biological Sciences, University of Rhode Island

SKILLS AND CERTIFICATIONS

ESRI ArcGIS – Geopatial statistics, spatial modeling

Statistics – R, PRIMER-E, SAS

Adobe Creative Suite

Mac and PC proficient

Seabed acoustic data visualization – QPS software including Fledermaus, CARIS,

CPR/First Aid

Small vessel (< 40') operation

SDI open water SCUBA

May 2017 4